<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY % poky SYSTEM "../poky.ent"> %poky; ] >
<!--SPDX-License-Identifier: CC-BY-2.0-UK-->

<chapter id='adt-intro'>
    <title>The Application Development Toolkit (ADT)</title>

    <para>
        Part of the Yocto Project development solution is an Application Development
        Toolkit (ADT).
        The ADT provides you with a custom-built, cross-development
        platform suited for developing a user-targeted product application.
    </para>

    <para>
        Fundamentally, the ADT consists of the following:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>An architecture-specific cross-toolchain and matching
                sysroot both built by the
                <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_DEV_URL;#build-system-term'>OpenEmbedded build system</ulink>.
                The toolchain and sysroot are based on a
                <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_DEV_URL;#metadata'>Metadata</ulink>
                configuration and extensions,
                which allows you to cross-develop on the host machine for the target hardware.
                </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>The Eclipse IDE Yocto Plug-in.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>The Quick EMUlator (QEMU), which lets you simulate target hardware.
                </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Various user-space tools that greatly enhance your application
                development experience.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <section id='the-cross-development-toolchain'>
        <title>The Cross-Development Toolchain</title>

        <para>
            The
            <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_DEV_URL;#cross-development-toolchain'>Cross-Development Toolchain</ulink>
            consists of a cross-compiler, cross-linker, and cross-debugger
            that are used to develop user-space applications for targeted
            hardware.
            This toolchain is created either by running the ADT Installer
            script, a toolchain installer script, or through a
            <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_DEV_URL;#build-directory'>Build Directory</ulink>
            that is based on your Metadata configuration or extension for
            your targeted device.
            The cross-toolchain works with a matching target sysroot.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id='sysroot'>
        <title>Sysroot</title>

        <para>
            The matching target sysroot contains needed headers and libraries for generating
            binaries that run on the target architecture.
            The sysroot is based on the target root filesystem image that is built by
            the OpenEmbedded build system and uses the same Metadata configuration
            used to build the cross-toolchain.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id='eclipse-overview'>
        <title>Eclipse Yocto Plug-in</title>

        <para>
            The Eclipse IDE is a popular development environment and it fully supports
            development using the Yocto Project.
            When you install and configure the Eclipse Yocto Project Plug-in into
            the Eclipse IDE, you maximize your Yocto Project experience.
            Installing and configuring the Plug-in results in an environment that
            has extensions specifically designed to let you more easily develop software.
            These extensions allow for cross-compilation, deployment, and execution of
            your output into a QEMU emulation session.
            You can also perform cross-debugging and profiling.
            The environment also supports a suite of tools that allows you to perform
            remote profiling, tracing, collection of power data, collection of
            latency data, and collection of performance data.
        </para>

        <para>
            For information about the application development workflow that uses the Eclipse
            IDE and for a detailed example of how to install and configure the Eclipse
            Yocto Project Plug-in, see the
            "<ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_DEV_URL;#adt-eclipse'>Working Within Eclipse</ulink>" section
            of the Yocto Project Development Manual.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id='the-qemu-emulator'>
        <title>The QEMU Emulator</title>

        <para>
            The QEMU emulator allows you to simulate your hardware while running your
            application or image.
            QEMU is made available a number of ways:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>
                    If you use the ADT Installer script to install ADT, you can
                    specify whether or not to install QEMU.
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    If you have cloned the <filename>poky</filename> Git
                    repository to create a
                    <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_DEV_URL;#source-directory'>Source Directory</ulink>
                    and you have sourced the environment setup script, QEMU is
                    installed and automatically available.
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    If you have downloaded a Yocto Project release and unpacked
                    it to create a
                    <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_DEV_URL;#source-directory'>Source Directory</ulink>
                    and you have sourced the environment setup script, QEMU is
                    installed and automatically available.
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    If you have installed the cross-toolchain tarball and you
                    have sourced the toolchain's setup environment script, QEMU
                    is also installed and automatically available.
                    </para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id='user-space-tools'>
        <title>User-Space Tools</title>

        <para>
            User-space tools are included as part of the Yocto Project.
            You will find these tools helpful during development.
            The tools include LatencyTOP, PowerTOP, OProfile, Perf, SystemTap, and Lttng-ust.
            These tools are common development tools for the Linux platform.
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para><emphasis>LatencyTOP:</emphasis> LatencyTOP focuses on latency
                    that causes skips in audio,
                    stutters in your desktop experience, or situations that overload your server
                    even when you have plenty of CPU power left.
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para><emphasis>PowerTOP:</emphasis> Helps you determine what
                    software is using the most power.
                    You can find out more about PowerTOP at
                    <ulink url='https://01.org/powertop/'></ulink>.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para><emphasis>OProfile:</emphasis> A system-wide profiler for Linux
                    systems that is capable of profiling all running code at low overhead.
                    You can find out more about OProfile at
                    <ulink url='http://oprofile.sourceforge.net/about/'></ulink>.
                    For examples on how to setup and use this tool, see the
                    "<ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_PROF_URL;#profile-manual-oprofile'>OProfile</ulink>"
                    section in the Yocto Project Profiling and Tracing Manual.
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para><emphasis>Perf:</emphasis> Performance counters for Linux used
                    to keep track of certain types of hardware and software events.
                    For more information on these types of counters see
                    <ulink url='https://perf.wiki.kernel.org/'></ulink>.
                    For examples on how to setup and use this tool, see the
                    "<ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_PROF_URL;#profile-manual-perf'>perf</ulink>"
                    section in the Yocto Project Profiling and Tracing Manual.
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para><emphasis>SystemTap:</emphasis> A free software infrastructure
                    that simplifies information gathering about a running Linux system.
                    This information helps you diagnose performance or functional problems.
                    SystemTap is not available as a user-space tool through the Eclipse IDE Yocto Plug-in.
                    See <ulink url='http://sourceware.org/systemtap'></ulink> for more information
                    on SystemTap.
                    For examples on how to setup and use this tool, see the
                    "<ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_PROF_URL;#profile-manual-systemtap'>SystemTap</ulink>"
                    section in the Yocto Project Profiling and Tracing Manual.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para><emphasis>Lttng-ust:</emphasis> A User-space Tracer designed to
                    provide detailed information on user-space activity.
                    See <ulink url='http://lttng.org/ust'></ulink> for more information on Lttng-ust.
                    </para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>

</chapter>
<!--
vim: expandtab tw=80 ts=4
-->
